Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
My Lady, I'm afraid I cannot serve you any more.
What's wrong? Calm yourself down.
The Household Department informed me that
Concubine Beauté appointed me to work in her palace.
I understand.
You are lucky to work for Concubine Beauté.
You may pack and leave right away.
Thank you, My Lady.
I am reluctant to leave.
Please take care of your health.
Jade,
call everyone in.
I've been sick for over two months.
I need to rest well, and my palace is overstaffed for that.
There is just one thing I need to tell you all today.
If you would like to leave my palace,
you may take a sycee from Jade and leave.
We all should congratulate Mr. Kang and Mr. Yin
on their new job for Concubine Beauté.
They will leave immediately.
My Lady has been kind to Mr. Kang,
and he has been as loyal as a dog.
But that doesn't matter as he now has a higher job.
Vermilion, it's not like that.
I am loyal to My Lady,
but Concubine Beauté has made up her mind.
I have no option.
You have no option? I never knew that
you can lead a cow to water and make it drink.
Please do not compromise your loyalty to My Lady
since you are devoted to serve her.
How about declining Concubine Beauté's request?
She will appreciate your loyalty
and I will apologize for my misunderstanding.
Don't talk the talk if you can't walk the walk.
Vermilion,
Mr. Kang will be loyal to whoever he serves.
Jade, give it to him.
Mr. Kang, farewell.
And you, Mr. Yin.
You have a lot to learn from your shifu.
Thank you, My Lady.
Go while we still have money for you!
My Lady will send you to the Department of Penalty
if you make a request after today.
Don't think twice!
I'm afraid I am incompetent to serve you, My Lady.
I will follow My Lady without a second thought.
Me as well.
I am indebted to you, My Lady.
I won't leave.
Why is that?
When my brother was desperately sick,
if My Lady had not sent Mr. Wen to take care of him,
my brother wouldn't still be alive.
I will spare no effort to repay you with my hard work.
If I don't pay you back in this life,
I will become a black ox that take you to the Pure Land.
Stop it.
I mean every word I say.
Okay, okay,
I will have to send for Mr. Wen if you break your forehead.
I do not want people to keep saying that
everyone in this palace is weak and sick.
It's very cold to stand guard at night.
Please prepare Xiao-Yunzi a thicker blanket.
Thank you, My Lady.
Not a day is easy for you all to follow a neglected concubine.
But you all are so good to me.
I don't know how I can ever repay you.
I promise you a life of ease as long as I live.
Thank you, My Lady.
The Household Department is such a bully.
They did not send good charcoal for My Lady.
Be quiet.
My Lady will feel bad if she hears it.
Is the water ready?
Yes.
The charcoal is too smokey to be used indoors.
I will go fill a hot water bottle.
Sure.
Peace to My Ladies.
It's very cold today.
I hope Attendant Sourire is having a good rest.
Peace to Lady Shen and Companion An.
It's freezing in here.
- How are you feeling today?
- Meizhuang.
- Huan.
- Lingrong.
Your hand is cold. Are you feeling better?
Just the same.
That is not good.
I like the color of your hairpin.
It must be a gift from His Majesty.
His Majesty is very fond of her.
Your palace is too cold for your recovery.
I brought you enough white charcoal to last for a while.
I saw Jinxi burning black charcoal.
The Household Department must be giving you trouble.
I will report to the Empress.
Inconsideration is inevitable for a powerless concubine.
Let's save the trouble.
They couldn't give me the cold shoulder
for your presence in the palace.
Now that I have charcoal for the winter.
Nothing can compare to the charcoal sent on a snowing day.
It's fortunate that you can keep a tolerant mind
towards Kang Luhai's heartless leave.
Out of sight, out of mind.
How do you mean?
Loyalty of the servants outweighs the number.
Indeed, I will be careful about mine as well.
And you, Lingrong.
Thank you for your reminder.
Sourire is having a slow recovery
probably because you are stressed by all this.
I'm all right. How about yourself?
Did you serve His Majesty overnight?
His Majesty must have forgotten me.
Don't worry, His Majesty is occupied with the war in the northwest.
You will serve him sooner or later.
I understand. I heard that His Majesty
has not visited the harem for over ten days.
Yes, that would worry the Empress Dowager.
You must be using hot water bottles in the winter.
I made this cover overnight for you.
The textile was our welcome gift when we moved in.
It's a waste to be made into a bottle cover.
Not at all, that is the best thing I can give you
- if you like.
- I do.
The Empress sent me to check the decorations around the palace.
I have to go now.
Certainly, walk safely.
I will visit you another day.
You don't have to come if it's cold outside.
It's okay, I like spending time with you.
Jinxi, please walk them out.
Take care, feel better soon.
My Lady, time for medicine.
How long will you keep doing this?
I'm afraid the medicine will harm your health.
It simply slows down my recovery.
Did anyone find out?
No, no one else knows.
But why would you hide from Lady Shen and Companion An?
Because I see them as my sisters.
They will not be affected if it comes to light.
It's nice to see you here, Lunar.
- Please have a seat.
- It's okay.
I went to visit Attendant Sourire with Lady Shen.
I'm dropping by for the stipend.
Go pack the stipend for Lady Shen.
You came from the Palace of Pearl Jade?
Yes, Lady Shen and Attendant Sourire are friends since childhood.
My Lady is concerned about Attendant Sourire's recovery.
I hope she's been taken good care of.
Not really.
Her palace is ill-equipped for the winter.
I can't imagine living there were My Lady not helping her.
Sorry to have troubled Lady Shen.
This must be the negligence of our department.
I will look into that right away.
Thank you for taking your time.
It must be an omission of your staff.
Gee, what brings you here, Madam Song Zhi?
Don't talk to me like that.
Our palace needs more gold paper to wrap new year gifts.
I'm here to get some for Her Highness in advance.
You should have informed me earlier.
Your palace was the first to receive gold paper,
double the amount of other palaces.
The Empress just had hers picked up.
I'm afraid we have to share the remaining gold paper
among the other concubines.
Huang Guiquan, do you need me to tell you how to do your job?
Her Highness's requests were never turned down.
Give her what you have and make it up to the other concubines later.
But...
The lower ranks don't deserve the gold paper, do they?
- Here you go.
- Thank you.
Yo, you got your stipend this month?
I thought Lady Shen was still forfeiting her stipend.
Huang Guiquan, you hear what I just said?
Do not try Her Highness's temper.
Aiyo, that's difficult.
It's bone-chilling cold.
Did you get the year-end bonus?
Yes.
The Household Department gave us in full amount
because of Lady Shen.
Thanks to Lady Shen,
she just had her gifts sent here.
Did she?
We will have a happy new year.
It's December 25th today.
I hope My Lady can feel better soon enough
to attend the imperial banquet on New Year's Eve.
It's okay. Jiang Fuhai came and read the edict of the Empress
that My Lady's is allowed to be absent from the banquet.
Great! We can stay up with My Lady to celebrate the new year.
Exactly.
His Majesty and Her Majesty.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Please don't feel inhibited at a family dinner.
Have a seat.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
You tell us to relax every time,
(Yun Li, Noble Prince Guo)
but no one listens.
You do, Prince XVII never feels inhibited.
And he is surprisingly punctual today.
I'm never late for a big meal.
Here's to Your Majesty,
wishing you and the country peace and prosperity.
Cheers!
Wishing Your Majesty happiness and longevity.
Long live the Emperor!
Bottoms up!
This is fine wine.
Consort Fleur, did you drink every drop?
Of course.
Your Majesty is in a good mood today.
News of victory came from the northwest this afternoon.
Nian Gengyao put down the rebellion
in the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau.
What a great general!
Congratulations, Your Majesty.
Congratulations! Your Majesty is at peace now.
Your brother did a fantastic job.
My brother renders good service on the front line,
and I will do my best in the harem.
I wish we had plum trees and cypresses in the yard.
It would look livelier on a snowy day.
We can put paper-cuts onto the windows
to liven up our palace.
Good idea! Can you go get colored paper and gold foil?
Yay! I'll go get it.
I'll go get scissors.
- I'll look for paper-cut patterns.
- I'll go with you!
Your Highness, Consort Honnête is hada seizure
and requests to see a doctor.
She is bad luck for the new year.
Request denied.
What if she sends for a doctor herself.
Tell the imperial doctors that I will take offence if anyone goes.
Yes, Your Highness.
To Your Majesty.
I didn't see Attendant Sourire today.
I told her not to come on such a cold day.
Jinxi, let me have a look.
Your peacock is coming alive.
- It's beautiful!
- Absolutely.
It cannot compare to the Two Gods of Harmony you made.
They are so full of life.
Exactly.
The Two Gods of Harmony are imagined.
I don't know what they look like.
I learnt that the best paper-cut artists can take a portrait of a person.
Sadly, I've never met one.
My Lady, there's one standing right in front of you.
Xiao-Yunzi made a portrait of you.
He's hiding it in his sleeve.
Really?
Xiao-Yunzi, don't be shy. Let me have a look.
Let us see.
(gasp)
It looks just like you.
Xiao-Yunzi, you are so talented!
Indeed.
Not at all, it doesn't do justice to your beautiful face.
I'll make a better one next time.
It does look like My Lady, but it also resembles Jade.
How can I compare to My Lady.
Come here.
Jade does look like me after living together all these years.
Why do I not look like you?
It will be scary if everyone looks like me.
But you took on my playfulness.
I heard about this custom in the palace
that you can make a wish by putting your favorite thing
on a tall tree on New Year's Eve. The taller the better!
My Lady, you can put the portrait onto a tall tree in the yard.
It will also make Xiao-Yunzi happy.
Good idea.
But not on the bare trees in the yard.
How about we put the portrait onto the blooming plum trees?
Fantastic!
The Garden of Leaning Plums is a good place to go to.
Are the flowers in white color?
No, they are pink with jade at the center.
Look like red clouds.
Nice.
Fragrant clouds of plum blossoms in the snow.
That must be gorgeous.
I've got to see it!
My Lady, you shouldn't go.
My Lady, you need to be better in health to go out in a snowy day.
And the Empress is aware that you are in quarantine.
We will be held responsible if Her Majesty finds out.
Exactly.
Everyone is at the banquet at this time.
I will wear a cloak to keep myself warm and inconspicuous.
I need to take a walk in such a long quarantine.
My Lady...
Leave me alone!
I'll go by myself.
Whoever follows me will be standing outside for the rest of tonight.
My Lady...
Prince V, I wish you peace and happiness.
Are the plum trees blooming?
Yes, against the frost.
I wish to see them.
But it's very cold outside.
How can their beauty not be appreciated?
It's okay.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
I'll take a walk by myself
to sober up.
- But, Your Majesty ...
- Your Majesty ...
I'll be fine.
Your Majesty.
Where's Your Majesty going?
What shall we do?
It's dark and slippery outside.
Prince XVII,
His Majesty left alone, but he has to
be taken care of on such a snowy night.
I noticed that we have red plum flowers today.
Consort Fleur had the banquet hall decorated.
She doesn't know.
I'll follow His Majesty. We'll be fine.
(Yu Ying'er)
Why do I have to do this on New Year's Eve?
That is not how you treat a newcomer to the palace!
Everyone here is probably wishing for His Majesty's affection.
I wish my family good health,
and myself a peaceful life in the palace.
I understand it is difficult to stay outside the incessant rivalries.
“If the northern wind can hear the plum flowers,
spare the blooming wishes for a peaceful spring."
Who is there?
Answer me or I'll have people searching the entire garden.
I am a maid working in the garden.
Are you educated? What is your name?
I am too humble to say my name.
Do not come over!
I'm taking off my socks. They are wet.
The flowers are just as beautiful as before.
"Same are the flowers time after time;
different are the beholders year after year."
Consort Fleur arranged plum flowers for the banquet.
It wasn't her intention.
I was too sentimental.
She didn't know what had happened
by the time I married her.
You still can't let go.
Of what?
I'm looking forward to the spring,
when you can come oftener to play Go.
I would love to.
But for now, I need a drink seeing the flowers.
I'll go with you.
Let's drink our fill for the plum in the snow.
There was another surprise.
I came across a talented maid.
Congratulations.
- You're back, My Lady.
- My Lady.
What is wrong?
Please have a cup of tea.
You must be frozen.
What happened?
(pause) I came across two cats.
I was scared.
My Lady is afraid of cats.
It must have been frightening to see two at once.
I'll make ginger tea to calm you down.
Many cats are kept in the palace.
They can get out of control sometimes.
You need to be careful in the future.
Did you make a wish?
I did.
But it was too cold to stay there.
I told you not to follow me.
Please forgive me.
But I couldn't put my mind at ease while Your Majesty walks alone.
So I followed Noble Prince Guo quietly.
The mantis catches the cicada while a siskin follows.
I was only looking at the cicada.
I have a task for you since you are here.
I need you to look for a knowledgeable maid
in the Garden of Leaning Plums.
That will make up for your mistake.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Please enlighten me how to test the knowledge of the maid.
Ask her what is the next line for
"If the northern wind can hear the plum flowers".
Yes.
Seems like Madiao [a gambling card game]
cannot keep them awake till midnight.
I am sleepy as well.
My Lady was in good luck.
Now we don't have lucky money for the new year.
No, you guys made me win.
I have a question about fabric patterns.
Who can wear a dragon brocade in the palace?
Why?
I was just wondering what people would wear for the banquet.
I see.
The dragon brocade is exclusively used by His Majesty,
or the most important princes.
Of the many princes of the prior emperor,
who would be invited to the new year banquet?
Prince V and Prince X.
And Prince XVII.
He is a half brother of His Majesty,
but they both were brought up by the Empress Dowager.
I learnt that Prince XVII is living like a wild crane.
He is also an unrivaled flute player.
Nine of the princes had a ruthless fight for the throne.
Prince XVII remained distinguished for his aversion to the fight.
That is true.
To fight is not always as wise as not to.
No, My Lady.
I hope so.
It's late. Sleep well, My Lady.
His Majesty has a couplet riddle for the Spring Festival.
Anyone able to solve it will be amply rewarded.
We would like to hear the riddle.
It would be fun even if we cannot solve it.
Listen up, the first line is
"If the northern wind can hear the plum flowers".
Does anyone know the second line.
"Spare the blooming wishes for a peaceful spring."
You've been playing absent-mindedly.
You won.
I can't match you at Go.
Your Majesty, I've tried my best to complete the task.
But ...
But you didn't know the answer to the riddle.
That must be a difficult job.
There's no excuse for failure to do your job.
I'm sorry.
Your Majesty must be thirsty after the game,
if Your Majesty would like a cup of tea before punishing me.
[Servants are not allowed to look the emperor in the face.]
Is the tea made of the snow on the plum flowers?
It smells like plum flowers.
I beg Your Majesty's pardon.
That is the smell of my clothes. Sorry for disturbing.
Your Majesty does have sweet servants.
I will ask my servants to smell better as well.
I don't remember seeing you.
When did you start working here?
"If the northern wind can hear the plum flowers,
spare the blooming wishes for a peaceful spring."
I was working in the Garden of Leaning Plums.
Mr. Su offered me the honor to work here for Your Majesty.
Was it cold walking all the way to here.
It stopped snowing.
Unlike the drenching night on New Year's Eve.
You did a good job.
I shall return to my work in the garden.
The garden is full of plum flowers,
but I need one in my palace.
You will stay here.
I thank Your Majesty.
What is your name?
My humble name is Yu Ying'er.
Yu Ying'er is given the title of Escort.
She will live in the Palace of Purity.
Long live the Emperor!
"Rather than the gold palaces in Heaven,
I would be drunk with the flowering plums in Luoyang."
Do you not understand what he said?
No, I hope Your Lordship can enlighten me.
It is a poem by Li Bai. [It is not. He's fooling her.]
This means His Majesty likes Li Bai's poems.
Thank Your Lordship, I understand.
I bid Your Lordship goodbye.
Where are you heading to?
I'm going to register the new concubine with the Household Department.
You will be rewarded for your hard work.
I dare not think of that.
When you deliver a package,
it is okay to be late than to hand over the wrong thing.
You can sing Kunqu Opera?
I learned it from my father. He's in a Kunqu troupe.
Your Lordship was saying "hand over the wrong thing".
Would you mind clarifying that for me?
Never mind.
A strange thing happened in the palace.
What is it?
His Majesty somehow became fond of
a maid from the Garden of Leaning Plums.
She became an Escort, and a Companion the day before last.
From the Garden of Leaning Plums?
Yes.
It is not uncommon for an emperor to like a maid.
His Majesty likes her a lot.
As much as he likes you?
Almost as much.
I heard that she can sing Kunqu.
That is a novelty.
I would also like a girl good at flower art and Kunqu.
However His Majesty likes her,
she will not rank above you for her humble background.
I know.
But Lingrong is not happy about that.
Right. She has not even served His Majesty yet.
She's fine with the other concubines serving His Majesty,
but this one was ten times humbler than her.
It worries her that they are at the same rank.
Does Lingrong not want to serve His Majesty?
His Majesty is a rare visitor to the harem.
He only visits his favorites when he comes.
You know how the people treat you in the palace.
You would live worse than a maid if you're not his favorite.
I can't believe you would feel that way.
His Majesty has always been very fond of you.
I'm just concerned.
What if some day he doesn't like me anymore?
That will never happen. His Majesty really likes you for
who you are, not to mention your family background.
I do hope so.
My Lady, gifts for the Lantern Festival have arrived.
[Latern Festival is Jan 15 in lunar calendar.]
Please go have a look.
I will see you later.
Peace to Lady Shen.
Thank you, Companion Yu.
His Majesty bestowed a sedan chair to escort me on the slippery roads.
Please pardon my inconvenience to greet you on the ground.
It's okay. How would you serve His Majesty had you had a fall?
I was going to pay respect to the Empress after greeting Consort Fleur.
Will you make way for me?
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.